听译、时间轴：刘巍然（学酥）
一般来说 我们使用复制的原因是希望系统变得更可靠
The reason we want replication is typically to make systems more reliable.
有各种各样的原因可能会使一个节点不可用
So, a node might be unavailable for all sorts of reasons.
节点可能会崩溃
It might crash.
节点可能会遇到硬件问题
It might have a hardware problem.
节点可能会因为例行维护而重启
It might be just rebooting due to routine maintenance.
我们假设一个节点在任何给定的时刻不可用的概率为p
Let's assume just there's some probability p that a node is unavailable at any given time.
我们进一步假定 一个节点是否不可用
And let's also assume that whether one node is unavailable
与另一个节点是否不可用 这两个事件是相互独立的
is independent from whether another node is unavailable.
也就是说 我们假设故障之间是不相关的
So, we're going to assume that faults are not correlated.
这个假设实际上不正确
This is not actually true.
有研究已经表明
There have been studies that have shown that
实际中 节点故障存在相关性
actually, faults do tend to be correlated in practice.
但这里我们只是为了做一些粗略的估计
But just for the purposes of some rough estimation,
我们现在假设故障之间是相互独立的
it's OK for now to assume that they are actually independent.
现在 p是一个节点出现故障的概率
So now, if p is the probability of any one node being faulty,
这意味着所有n个副本都出现故障的概率是p^n
that means the probability of all n replicas being faulty is p^n.
我们也可以算出一个或多个节点出现故障的概率
And we can work out what is the probability of one or more being faulty.
我们可以制作出这样一个表格
And we can make a little table.
这个表格告诉我们
And what this table shows here is
如果我们查看至少一个节点出现故障的这一列
if you look at the column for at least one node being faulty,
随着副本数量的增加
as you increase the number of replicas,
我们几乎可以肯定 在任意给定时刻 至少有一个节点会出现故障
it becomes almost certain that at least one of them is faulty at any given time.
从这个角度看 系统的可靠性会随着副本数量的增加而降低
So, in that sense, as you add replicas, the system becomes less reliable,
因为任意节点都有可能出现故障 如果你增加了太多的副本
because given anyone has a chance of failing, as you have lots of replicas,
则在任意时刻 总会有一个副本出现故障
there'll always be one that has failed at any moment.
然而 如果我们考察所有副本全部出现故障的概率
However, if we take the probability of all of them being faulty,
此概率会随着副本数量的增加而指数级降低
this probability decreases exponentially as you increase the number of replicas.
即使你不考虑所有副本都出现故障的概率
And even if you consider not the probability of all of them failing,
只考虑一半副本出现故障的概率
but just the probability of half of the replicas failing,
此概率也会随着副本数量的增加而指数级降低
this probability also decreases exponentially with the number of replicas.
这就是为什么我们可以实现容错的原因
So, this is why we can achieve fault tolerance,
因为我们可以允许一部分节点不可用
because it's OK if some of the nodes are unavailable,
我们可以允许一部分副本不可用
some of the replicas are unavailable,
我们只需要保证当至少大多数副本可用时
we just have to make sure that given at least most of the replicas are available,
系统仍然可以继续运作
then the system continues working,
这样我们就可以获得非常高的可靠性了
and then we can actually achieve very high reliability.
我们来看看我们希望容错复制系统
So, let's look at one particular property that we might want
可以满足的一个特定性质
in a fault-tolerant replicated system.
这个性质叫写后读一致性
And that is called read-after-write consistency.
写后读一致性的意思是
So, what happens here is that
客户端先写入某个数据 随后还能再次读取相同的数据
a client first writes some data, and then it reads the same data back again.
你可能很自然的期望
And you would naturally expect that
客户端随后读取到的数据和之前写入的数据是一样的
that client to just to then see the data that it has just written.
这里 客户端想要设置键x的值为v_1
So, here, client wants to set the key x to the value v_1.
我们在此操作上附加一个时间戳t_1
And we attach a timestamp of t_1 to that operation.
客户端将更新操作发送给两个副本数据库A和B
It sends that update to both replicas of the database A and B.
副本B收到并处理更新操作
The replica B receives that update and processes it
而副本A不可用 因此A没有处理更新操作
whereas replica A is unavailable, and so the update is not processed by A.
随后 客户端希望再次读取x所关联的值
Then, subsequently, the client goes and wants to read x again.
但因为某种原因 情况发生了逆转
But for some reason, now the things have flipped around.
现在 A可用 而B不可用
And now, A is available, but B is not available.
因此 客户端从A处得到的响应
And so, now, the response that the client gets back from A
与客户端之前写入的值v_1不相等
does not reflect that value v_1 that has been written.
客户端得到的响应是写入v_1之前
So, the response is going to be some earlier value v_0
副本稍早时持有的值v_0
that the replicas had before this scenario here started.
这种情况违反了写后读一致性
So, in this case, we have violated read-after-write consistency,
这有些糟糕
which is kind of unfortunate,
因为如果你写入某个数据 结果数据丢失了 过了一会数据又出现了
because it's very confusing if you write some data, and then the data disappears,
这种现象会非常令人困惑
and then, sometime later, the data reappears again.
这种情况下 我们可以做到的是
Now, what we could do here in this case is that
必须在两个副本中完成读操作和写操作
the read and write have to go to both replicas.
这样我们就可以保证不会遇到上述交叉读写问题
And so, that way we would ensure that we don't get this crossover problem
即只有一个副本更新了数据 而我们又从另一个副本读取数据
where only one of the replicas has seen the update and we read from the other one.
但现在 如果我们要求两个副本必须都完成读操作和写操作
But now, if we require a read or write to go to both replicas,
那么系统就无法满足容错性
then the system is not fault-tolerant,
因为只要其中一个副本不可用
because if just one of the two replicas becomes unavailable,
我们就无法处理所有读操作和写操作了
then we can't process reads or writes anymore.
我们可以利用quorum来解决这个问题
So, we can solve this problem using something called a quorum.
在这个例子中 我们的做法是使用一个3选2的quorum
And what we do here is here I've got an example quorum of 2-out-of-3.
当我们想执行写操作时 客户端向所有3个副本发送写请求
And so, when we want to make a write, the client sends its request to all 3 replicas.
我们假设这里有3个副本
We're going to assume here there are 3 replicas.
由于某种原因 请求只到达了3个副本中的2个副本
And for some reason, the request reaches 2-out-of-3 of these 2 replicas.
请求到达了B和C 但是没有到达A
So, the request reaches B and C, but not A.
随后 B和C响应客户端说
And then, B and C are going to respond to the client, saying
“好的 我收到你更新这一特定键x的请求了”
“OK, yes, I got your request to update this particular key x.”
一旦收到了两个正面响应 客户端就开心了
And once the client has collected two positive responses, then it's happy.
请求没有成功传输到A处也没问题
So, the fact that the request didn't get through to A is OK.
可能A不可用 但只要B和C响应了请求就没问题
So, maybe A is unavailable, as long as B and C still respond, that's still fine.
接下来 客户端要执行读操作 它再次向3个副本发送读请求
Now, second, the client goes to read, and it sends its read again to all 3 replicas.
像之前一样 只有2个副本收到了请求
As before, only 2 of them get it.
此时 由于某种原因
And so, in this case, for some reason,
发送给C的读请求未传输成功 但发送给A和B的读请求传输成功
the read to C doesn't go through, but the reads to A and B do go through.
这种情况下 客户端将收到来自A和B的响应
And so, in this case, now, the client will receive responses from A and B.
客户端将从B得到期望的正确响应 因为B看到了写请求
It will get the correct response that was expecting from B, because B has seen the write.
客户端将从A得到过期的响应 因为A没有看到写请求
It will get an outdated response from A, because A didn't get the write.
但客户端至少可以从一个响应中得到更新值
But at least one of the responses that the client got back has the updated value.
现在 客户端可以通过时间戳t_0和t_1
And so, now, the client can use the timestamps t_0 and t_1
得知哪个值才是最近更新的
to figure out which is the more recent update.
这允许客户端知道
And this now allows the client to know
给应用回复的正确数据应该是什么
what the correct response should be that it returns to the application.
应用心满意足 因为现在满足写后读一致性了
And the application is happy, because it has read-after-write consistency.
我们到底要怎么做才能实现这个目标呢？
So, what do we have to do exactly to achieve this?
我们使用quorum
We use quorums.
当你想向一定数量的副本执行写操作时
And whenever you want to make a write to some number of replicas,
仅当至少收到来自w个副本的确认时
the write will be considered successful
你才认为写入操作成功执行完毕
as long as it has been acknowledged by at least w replicas.
这就是quorum写
So, this is our write quorum.
随后 当你想读数据时 你需要至少收到来自r个副本的确认
And then, when you read, if you get a response back from at least r replicas,
现在 我们得到了算法的两个参数w和r
so now, we have w and r as our two parameters of this algorithm,
我们要求
and we require that
w和r的和要严格大于系统中的副本数量
the sum of w and r is strictly greater than the number of replicas in the system.
在我们的例子中 w等于2、r等于2、n等于3
So, in our example, here w was 2, r was 2, and n was 3.
而2+2>3
So, 2+2>3.
因此 这种情况下 我们可以保证读到的值一定是之前写入的值
And so, in this case, we can guarantee that the read will see the previously written value,
或者读到的值是其他客户端通过并发写入覆盖后的值
or maybe it was concurrently overwritten by another client,
但读到的一定是最新的值
but it will see an up-to-date value,
如果r+w≤n
whereas if this r+w≤n,
那我们有可能无法读到我们期望的值
it could happen that we don't get the value back that we were expecting.
这里的思想是
So, the idea here is that
写操作会在节点的某个子集下完成
the write goes to some subset of nodes,
读操作会在节点的某个子集下完成
the read goes to some subset of nodes,
我们希望两个子集有重叠
and we want those two subsets to overlap.
如果我们有r+w>n 满足quorum条件
And we can guarantee that they will overlap in at least one replica
我们就可以保证两个子集中至少包含1个重叠副本
if we have this r+w>n, this quorum condition.
另一种理解方法是
Another way of putting this is that
我们有两个子集 这两个节点子集必须有非空交集
we have these two subsets, and subsets of nodes have to have a non-empty intersection.
例如 如果我们有5个节点
So, for example, if we have 5 nodes,
我们要求写quorum为3、读quorum为3
we could require a write quorum of 3 and a read quorum of 3,
这样就满足了quorum条件
that would satisfy this condition.
这种情况下 两个节点子集总能保证
And in this case, those two subsets of nodes are always guaranteed
至少包含1个公共节点
to have at least 1 element in common.
两个子集总包含非空交集
So, they will have a non-empty intersection.
构建quorum的常见方法叫多半quorum
One common way of constructing these quorums is what are called majority quorums,
我们一般假设存在奇数个节点
where we're going to assume that we have an odd number of nodes,
只要读quorum和写quorum
and as long as the read quorum and the write quorum
都严格大于节点数量的一半 就满足quorum条件了
are strictly more than half of the number of nodes, then it's fine.
即要求3选2、5选3、7选4 以此类推
So, that means we require 2-out-of-3, we require 3-out-of-5, 4-out-of-7, and so on.
这意味着
And this means now that
在3选2情况下
in a 2-out-of-3 case,
只要其他两个节点可以响应 我们就能容忍1个节点不可用
we can tolerate 1 node being unavailable as long as the other 2 respond.
在5选3情况下
In a 3-out-of-5 case,
只要剩余的3个节点可以响应 我们就能容忍2个节点不可用
we can tolerate 2 replicas being unavailable as long as the 3 remaining ones respond,
以此类推
and so on.
这就是与quorum相关的全部内容了
So, this is all the quorums are about really.
我们讲完了quorum读和quorum写
Now that we've done these quorum reads and writes,
我们还可以做的一件事是
one thing that we can do is
客户端可以帮助这些不同的副本再次回到同步状态
for the client can help get those different replicas back in sync with each other again.
在这个例子中 客户端从A收到了过期值
So, in this case, here the client received an outdated value from A,
客户端从B收到了最新值
and it received the up-to-date value from B,
客户端没有收到C的响应
and it didn't receive anything at all from C.
客户端现在已经知道
And so, the client already knows now that
A、B和C的状态是不一致的
A and B and C are inconsistent with each other.
此时 客户端可以帮忙解决不一致的问题
And so, the client can help clean the situation up
方法是把更新值发送回A和C
by actually sending the update back to A and C.
C可能不需要获得更新值
So, C might not need it,
因为C可能已经得到了更新值 只是没有响应问询
because it might be that C actually has the up-to-date value, but it just didn't respond.
再发送一次更新值也不会带来什么危害
There's no harm in sending it again.
我们确实希望能给A发送更新值
And certainly, we want to send the update to A
使A和B都可以拥有更新值v_1
so that now A and B both have the updated value v_1.
请注意 我们这里使用的是原始操作的时间戳
So, notice that we use the original timestamp here,
因为这是数据检索操作 而不是一个新的集合操作
because this is effectively just a retrieve, this is not a new set operation.
因此 使用原始操作的时间戳才是正确的
And therefore, it's correct to use the right timestamp,
客户端可以帮助副本传播正确的数据取值
and the client can thus help propagate the values between the replicas.
我们前面讨论的反熵
So, we have the anti-entropy that we discussed earlier
是一种让副本恢复到同步状态的机制
as one mechanism for the replicas to get back in sync.
这里介绍的读修复过程
And this process here, read repair,
是另一种帮助副本恢复到同步状态的方法
is another way that helps the replicas get back in sync with each other.